Guide to the Robert Colodny Papers ALBA.211
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert Colodny Papers
1937-2002, (Bulk 1960-1995)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Colodny, Robert Garland.
ALBA.211
5.25 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
Robert Colodny (1915-1997) fought with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War. He returned to the U.S. in 1938 with a severe head injury. He recovered and served in with the U.S. Army in Alaska during World War II. Colodny received his Ph.D. in history and philosophy in 1950 and joined the faculty of the University of Pittsburgh in 1959. In 1961, a Pennsylvania State representative accused Colodny of being a Communist sympathizer, jeopardizing his faculty position at the University of Pittsburgh. After a HUAC hearing and a University inquiry, Colodny was cleared and his position secured. This collection documents Colodny’s writings from World War II; his work as a writer and editor of academic, political and historical material; his correspondence and activities with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades (VALB); and his lifelong involvement in a range of progressive causes.
Provenance
The Robert Colodny Papers were donated to the Tamiment Library at New York University in 1997, by his wife, Margaret S. Colodny.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Robert Garland Colodny (1915-1997) was born in Phoenix, Arizona. In 1936, after having been expelled from Columbia University for refusing to take certain courses, Colodny became a chemistry student at the University of Chicago; there he expressly sought out recruiters for the International Brigades. In February 1937, Colodny sailed for Spain on the Isle de France. By late summer, he had been shot between the eyes, contracted gangrene of the brain, and was expected to die. But he recovered, and, though bandaged, weak and blind in one eye, was sent back to a front in the Aragon Mountains. It was not long before he was stricken with a high fever, however, and in March 1938, Colodny was granted permission to leave Spain on a sealed train to Paris. He sailed for the U.S. in April, partially paralyzed and blinded on the left side.
Despite his health history, Colodny joined the U.S. Army in 1941, and served for four years, stationed in the Aleutian Islands in Alaska in Army Intelligence alongside fellow-sergeant Dashiell Hammett. With Hammett, Colodny produced a Company newsletter, The Adakian, designed to boost troop morale, and co-authored a book commissioned by the Army, The Battle of the Aleutians; they also co-wrote and broadcast a radio program.
Colodny earned his doctorate in history and philosophy from the University of California, Berkeley in 1950. His Masters Thesis on the Spanish Civil War was later published as The Struggle for Madrid(1958). In 1959, Colodny joined the history faculty of the University of Pittsburgh. Two years later, Pennsylvania State Representative John T. Walsh accused Colodny of being a Communist sympathizer for having made a statement supporting the Cuban revolution. This was one of the last anti-Communist investigations in the nation's history. His career in jeopardy, Colodny fought a year-long battle to clear his name. In addition to his appearances before the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC), where he was cleared after stating that he had been misquoted on Cuba and denying membership in the Communist Party, Colodny underwent a separate investigation by the University of Pittsburgh. Ultimately Chancellor Edward Litchfield stood behind Colodny, declaring the University's strong commitment to protecting academic freedom. Colodny taught at the University of Pittsburgh until his retirement in 1984.
Colodny remained politically involved with progressive causes, including the civil rights and anti-Vietnam War movements, throughout his life. His expertise in the many aspects of the history of science led to his activism for a number of environmental causes. Colodny was a member of VALB, regularly contributing to the group's publication, The Volunteer, and dedicating his energy especially to preserving the memory and lessons of the Spanish Civil War. He also served on VALB's historical preservation committee.
In addition to his voluminous scientific writing and book reviewing, Colodny wrote and lectured extensively on the political implications of the Spanish Civil War. He also edited, consulted and contributed to many book, radio, film, and television projects on the subject, including work on Death in the Olive Groves: The Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War by Arthur Landis; and Prisoners of the Good Fight by Carl Geiser.
Colodny died in 1997 of colon cancer.
Sources:
The Struggle for Madrid: The Central Epic of the Spanish Conflict, 1936-37(New York: Paine-Whitman, 1958)
Spain: The Glory and the Tragedy(New York: Humanities Press, 1970)
Spain and Vietnam: The Fight for Freedom(New York: Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1967)
Scope and Content Note
Series I, General Files.
Files in Series I include Colodny’s World War II writings, some co-written by Dashiell Hammett; materials from Colodny’s academic career; papers related to his involvement in a range of progressive causes; writings analyzing and commemorating the Spanish Civil War; materials documenting conferences, lectures, and other Spanish Civil War-related activities; and typescripts and correspondence related to Colodny’s work as contributing writer and editor on academic, political, and historical projects.
Files documenting Colodny’s academic freedom case at the University of Pittsburgh include correspondence, hearing transcripts, and newspaper clippings. General correspondence includes exchanges with colleagues and students; correspondence with Russian mathematical linguist V.V. Nalimov, with typescripts of Nalimov’s writings on the history of science edited by Colodny; and correspondence and typescripts of Colodny’s work with Israeli academician Arie S. Issar on the philosophy of science and the evolution of water resources. Correspondence documents years of work with VALB and exchanges with Spanish Civil War veterans, including Moe Fishman, Harry Fisher, Edward Barsky, Alvah Bessie, Joseph Brandt, and Fredericka Martin. Other correspondence includes notes from Malcolm Cowley, and photocopies of notes from Lillian Hellman, Gore Vidal, and C.P. Snow.
Typescripts include Colodny’s writings for the radio broadcast Corpus Duende: Echoes of the Spanish Civil War, which was performed by Eli Wallach; presentations at conferences on environmental issues, the Spanish Civil War, and global peace; and assorted book reviews. There are also a number of published book reviews of Colodny’s work.
Colodny’s work as an editor is further reflected in this series in the typescript of an anthology which he compiled and introduced, Fate and Hope: Echoes of the Anti-Fascist Struggles; as well as correspondence and partial typescripts of work by fellow veterans Arthur Landis and Carl Geiser. Writings by others include several essays by Willard C. Frank, Jr. about naval operations during the Spanish Civil War.
Other papers in this series document Colodny’s tour in Alaska during World War II. Included here are typescripts for his radio show, “The World in Review”; and publications about battles in the Aleutians written with Hammett, including a reprint of The Capture of Attu: Tales of World War II in Alaska.
Series II, Oversize Materials, Scrapbook, Audio- and Videotapes.
This series is comprised of original issues of The Adakian, the newsletter produced and written by Colodny and Dashiell Hammett in Alaska during World War II, as well as typescripts for radio shows broadcast on July 4th and V-J Day, 1945. Also in this series is a scrapbook of news clippings dating principally from 1961, when Colodny was under investigation by HUAC; two videotaped talks by Colodny; and an undated audio-tape of a Teach-In.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
Organized into 2 series:
Missing Title
I: General Files
II: Oversize Materials, Scrapbook, Audio- and Videotapes.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Carl Geiser Papers.
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Arthur H. Landis Papers.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Robert Colodny Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some audiovisual materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information, to request digitization of materials, and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Veterans |z United States |v Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Aleutian Islands (Alaska) |x History, Military.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Newsletters.; Correspondence.; Articles.; Aleutian Islands (Alaska); Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; University of Pittsburgh; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Nalimov, V. V. (Vasiliĭ Vasil'evich), 1910-1997; Landis, Arthur H., 1917-1986; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Issar, A.; Hammett, Dashiell, 1894-1961; Geiser, Carl; Frank, Willard C.
- Series I: General Files
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA): General, undated, 1971-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA): General, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adventures of Tim and Twinkles, 1981, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adler, Mortimer J.: Institute for Philosophical Resources, 1953, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Institute for Marxist Studies (AIMS), 1965, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aub, Max: Writings by, undated, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barsky, Edward, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bessie, Alvah, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Book Notes (Univ. of Pittsburgh, Colodny editor), undated, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brandt, Joseph, undated, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brinkley, David, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Campaign for Peace and Democracy/East and West, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - China: Articles, pamphlets, speeches, undated, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - China: Colodny visit and Spanish Civil War involvement, 1974-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Colodny: Applications for faculty positions, 1948-1958 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Colodny: Articles about, undated, 1967-1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Colodny: Biographical, undated, 1950-1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Colodny: Congressional Subpoenas, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Colodny: Interview with (transcript), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Colodny: Memorial tributes, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Colodny: Mexico, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Colodny: Passport materials, 1937-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Colodny: Professional memberships, undated, 1949, 1981-1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Colodny: Retirement, undated, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Colodny: U.S. Army, 1943-1945, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Articles on, undated, 1961, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Correspondence and reports, 1960-1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Cuba/Castro controversy, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Mulcahy Thesis, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Sourwine, J.G. (U.S. Senate, Dept. of Justice), 1961-1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Student petition, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Transcript of Inquiry (Part 1), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Colodny Case (Univ. of Pittsburgh): Transcript of Inquiry (Part 2), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Committee for a Democratic Far Eastern Policy, c.1952 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Communications Workers of America, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Communist Party (France), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Corpus Duende: Echoes of the Spanish Civil War: Performance with Eli Wallach (WQED), 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, A, undated, 1947-1987 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, B, 1958-1996 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, C, 1965, 1967-1995 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, D, 1960-1995 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, E, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, F, 1955-1995 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, G, 1960-1997 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, H - I, undated, 1961-1994 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, J, 1956-1990 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, K, 1967-1995 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, L, 1958-1995 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, M, 1957-1996 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, N, 1983-1997 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, O, undated, 1966-1995 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, R, 1964-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, S, undated, 1957-1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, T, undated, 1966-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, U, 197_, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, V, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, W, undated, 1965-1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Y, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Foreign language, 1949-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: General, 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cowley, Malcolm, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Crofton, B. (Ph.D. candidate), undated, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cuba crisis: Articles and publicity, undated, 1960-1962, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cuba crisis: Correspondence, undated, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dallet, Joseph, Jr.: Memorial Fund, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ecology: Articles, 1986-1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ecology: Correspondence about and notes, undated, 1973-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Fate and Hope: Bibliography and notes, undated, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fate and Hope: Correspondence, undated, 1968, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fate and Hope: Research material and notes, undated, 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fate and Hope: Chapter 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fate and Hope: Chapter 2, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Fate and Hope: Chapter 3, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Fate and Hope: Chapter 4, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fate and Hope: Chapter 4 (cont.), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fate and Hope: Chapter 5, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Fate and Hope: Chapters 6, 7, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Fate and Hope: Epilogue, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fisher, Harry, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Fishman, Moe, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Franklin, Ursula, 1975-1990 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - French Underground circular, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Fulbright, J.W. (U.S. Senator), 1961, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Fund for the Republic: Application rejected, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Gatens, Rosanna: Dissertation work (Ph.D. student), 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Geiser, Carl: Prisoners of the Good Fight(Colodny editing and introduction), 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Green, Nan, 1947, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Hellman, Lillian, 1966, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - History of Biology Project, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Institute for Scientific Information, 1980-1996 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - International Samovar Club, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Issar, Arie S.: (Colodny Editing, Introduction, Epilogue), 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Issar, Arie S.: Correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Issar, Arie S.: Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Issar, Arie S.: Writings by, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Landis, Arthur: Death in the Olive Groves(Colodny work on), 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Lardner, James: Memorial Fund and memoir of, 1939-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mantoux, Etienne: The Carthaginian Peace(Colodny preface), 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Matthews, Herbert, 1957, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Martin, Fredericka, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Masterpiece or Potboiler: Symposium on For Whom the Bell Tolls, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mendelsohn, Everett, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Montaux, Paul, 1936, 1957, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Monument to the American Volunteers in Spain, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Murrow, Edward R., 1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Articles, 1982-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Correspondence, 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: In the Labyrinth of Language(reviews and text), 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: ISI Press Correspondence, 1979-1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: Realms of Unconscious(reviews), 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Nalimov, V. V.: "Spontaneity of Consciousness" (on Hegel), 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Nathan, Otto, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Nelson, Steve, undated, 1985-1993 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Obituaries and memorials (by R.C.), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - O'Casey, Sean, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Opus Dei, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Ortiz, Bobbye, 1958, 1972-1990 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Orwell, George: Conference at Southern Illinois University, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Osipenko, A.S., 1989 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Patai, Frances, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Pauling, Linus, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Peace and Freedom Party, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Philosophy of Science: Articles, undated, 1957-1986 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Philosophy of Science: Correspondence, undated, 1964-1992 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Philosophy of Science: Publication business and reviews, undated, 1961-1987 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Prague events, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Public interest and global politics: Correspondence, 1959-1985 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Public interest and global politics: Events, 1959-1985 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Public interest and global politics: Nicaragua, Iran/Contra, South America articles, pamphlets, leaflets, 1965-1987 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Radosh, Ronald: Responses to article by, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Russian article (from Novy Mir, 1987, n.7), undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Science books and films: Reviews, 1974-1996 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Science and Society: Corresp., etc., undated, 1964-2002 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Segre, Sergio: Interview with, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Siege of Madrid: Dissertation research, 1947-1952 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Siege of Madrid: Chapters 1-3, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Siege of Madrid: Chapter 3, Epilogue, Bibliography, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Skywriter (Fourth Fighter Command): Colodny article, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Snow, C. P., 1957-1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Social/Political activities: Conferences, fundraising, articles, undated, 1958-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Southworth, Herbert: Letter and review, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Spain: Committee for a Democratic Spain, 1969-1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Spain: Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Spain: Maps, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Spain: People's Olympics, 1936, 1968-1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Spain: Politics: Articles, undated, 1940-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Spain: Politics: Presentations, newsletters, events, reports, undated, 1963-1979 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Spain: U.S. Military bases, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Spain: Years of Revolution: Shooting script, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Spanish Civil War: Archive of the International Brigades (Moscow), undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Spanish Civil War: Articles, undated, 1966-1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Spanish Civil War: Background material, undated, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Spanish Civil War: Bibliographies, undated, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Spanish Civil War: Bibliography project, 1966-1971 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Civil War: Biographies of veterans, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Spanish Civil War: City College veterans, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Spanish Civil War: Film projects and reviews, 1966-1995 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Spanish Civil War Historical Society, undated, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Spanish Civil War: Israel/Palestine veterans, undated,1973 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Spanish Civil War: Naval and other military operations (articles by Willard C. Frank, Jr.), 1978-1994 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Spanish Civil War: Poetry about, undated, 1980, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Spanish Civil War: Polish veterans, undated, 1972-1985 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Spanish Civil War: Publicity for books about, 1979-1994 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Spanish Civil War: Research material, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Spanish Civil War: Teaching materials, 1986-1995 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Spanish Civil War: Television and radio projects, 1962-1999 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Spanish Civil War: "U.S. Political Culture of the 1930s and American Response to" (Smithsonian symposium), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Spanish Civil War: Veterans: Articles, 1962-1995 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Spanish Civil War: Veterans' rights campaign, undated, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Speeches and Presentations: General, 1959-1986 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Speeches and Presentations: Hiroshima Commemoration, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Speeches and Presentations: History of Science, 1987-1990 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Speeches and Presentations: "Spain Remembered" (Penn State), 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Speeches and Presentations: Teach-Ins: "Words for Peace", 1967-1984 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Swoboda, Wolfram, 1967-1982 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Teaching: General, 1959-1974 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Teaching: History of Science, 1955-1968 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Teaching: Modern Europe, 1959-1986 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Teaching: Philosophy and Literature in the Age of Crisis, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Teaching: Students, 1977-1985 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Teaching: University of Kansas, 1958-1972 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Technology and Society (Erie, Pennsylvania), 1978-1989 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Time for Miracles: TV Film (consultant), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Travel: Austria, Hungary, Czechoslovakia, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - University of California Graduate Work: FBI interference, 1946-1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - University of Kansas, 1957-1959 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - University of Pittsburgh: Correspondence, 1959-1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - University of Pittsburgh: General articles, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Correspondence, undated, 1949-1996 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - VALB: General, undated, 1951-1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - VALB: Historical Commission, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - VALB vs. Subversive Activities Control Board (SACB), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 10)